And your pastor thinks he's Caruso.
Well, he can sing, surely.
I'm hoping the large turnout today is
not only curiosity as to how well the
pastor preaches.
I have been assured that the new pulpit
will arrive a week
Wednesday, Reverend Fitzsimmons. It's a
poor workman who blames his tools.
Sturdy pulpit means a sturdy church.
Well, let's get to my sermon then.
My colleagues in Toronto congratulated
me on my posting at Avonlea.
They said that the sins on this calm
island must be small,
inconsequential.
Do you know what I told them?
There are no such things as small sins.
Ask Lot's wife. Turn to a
pillar of salt simply for looking over
her shoulder.
A small misdeed. Not to mention what you
do to Falado. And yet the consequences
were great.
Sins are like the piranha fish of the
Amazon.
They gather and multiply until the muddy
water boils with their perfidy.
And the poor sinner's flesh is ripped.
and torn until nothing but polished
white bone remains.
Felix, don't feed the dog from the
table.
It's just a bone, Felicity.
Apparently, the new minister's luggage
included a box that was three times the
size of a steamer trunk and weighed
absolutely nothing.
What could that be?
Pipe.
Elvira Lawson told me.
It seems the Reverend Fitzsimmons
likes... What, a height?
Oh, I'm sure he'll work out fine.
Well, I think he confuses piety with
loudness.
Reverend Fitzsimmons is young and
perhaps a little overenthusiastic.
He bellows like a steer.
What'd I say? Do you think you could
behave yourself while your aunt is here,
Felix, dear?
And occasionally when she's not?
That's why I don't want Felix around
during our meeting. He blurts things.
What meeting?
Oh, yes, Alec. While you were visiting
Roger in Halifax, Felicity arranged a
discussion group.
Called a colicky something or other. The
Avonlea Young Women's Colloquium for
Social Betterment. Who cares about you
dumb old girls' meetings?
You see what I mean, Mother?
You'll be fine.
Alec, before we get into a domestic
implodio, shouldn't we...
Oh, yes, yes, of course.
Janet, Roger was looking through some of
Mother's things, and he came
across a box of very special mementos,
things that meant a lot to Mother and
whole family. Hattie and Olivia insist
that this be bequeathed to you.
Oh, kind of you.
Ooh.
Well, very grand.
And big.
It's wonderful.
It belonged to our great grandmother.
Children.
It's very beautiful, Mother. This is a
daguerreotype that she had done in 1846
in New York City.
She was a very imposing woman.
Wasn't she?
It makes her look so regal.
Well, yes, but surely this is far too
grand a gift to give to a mere
relative by marriage.
No, no, no. Olivia and Hattie wanted you
to have it, and I agree.
I don't know how or
when, but I promise you I will repay
your kindness.
To great -grandma -ma, then.
Great -grandma -ma. Indeed.
Oh!
It's a fear that if I rub my wort with a
dead man's spit, it'll miraculously
vanish.
I'm trying to count. Go away.
Why are you so cranky, Felicity?
Didn't you like Father's gift?
He bought me a doll.
Me, too.
Yes, but you're a child. You like dolls.
I am a grown woman.
You hear that a tribe in Africa can
shrink heads down to the size of a
fist?
Secrets of the occult?
Why would Father buy you grass?
You're just jealous because he doesn't
like your presents.
I think I should have gotten Great
-Great -Grandmother's comb.
Mother just hasn't got the cheekbones to
wear that sort of ornament.
At least you got a present. Digger
didn't get anything.
Alec, I'm coming.
Absolutely not, Felicity.
I'm sure none of the other girls in your
consortium... Floquium. Yes. The social
betterment. Yeah, well, whatever. The
answer is no, you may not put your hair
up. But, Mother, you are wearing your
new comb.
And seeing as it is so beautiful, I
thought... No, Felicity. And besides,
my very special gift.
Mother, when are you and Father going to
realize that I'm grown up? Perhaps when
you quit stamping your feet.
I thought you were going to wear the
comb today.
Oh, well, I thought the Avonlea sewing
circle was hardly the right place to
unveil such a thing.
Ah, you wanted a more special occasion,
is that it?
He wants us to talk about Avonlea's
social ills.
Do we have social ill?
Comey Ray, your brother Edward was seen
swimming in the all together with
nothing on.
We saw him diving for turtles at Hodgins
Pond. There were lots of naked boys
there. It seems to me that spying is
more of a social ill than swimming.
Good afternoon.
Close your mouth.
You look like a bunch of ignorant
country girls.
Felicity, you look wonderful.
Deportment is the first consideration of
every stylish young woman.
Now, ladies, if you'll please turn to
your agendas.
We're going to talk about hairstyle?
Our first topic of discussion, the
French bob.
Could it happen here?
Certainly not.
And why not? Because this is not France.
What does the French bob have to do with
social ills?
I don't know, but I wouldn't be caught
dead in one.
What news did Alec bring a pallet back,
Janet?
Oh, not much, Clara.
He and his brother Roger spent most of
their time digging through old junk.
Air rooms, I think you mean, Janet.
Well, some families past me downs are
worth quite a lot of money. Point of
a few treasures were uncovered.
Like my new comb?
Great -grandmama's comb.
Oh, there's a story.
Whilst the Americans were attacking Fort
George during the War of 1812, you
know. Grandmama was loading muskets for
our side, you see, and just
when defeat seemed imminent, great
-grandmama seized a musket and,
employing her considerable marksmanship,
turned the tide against the marauding
Yankees.
Long,
beautiful, raven hair kept falling
forward into the flintlock.
A dashing young captain came to the
rescue and tied it back with a leather
thong. Thus, when Fort George was saved,
great -grandmama was presented with the
very comb which is now bestowed upon our
Janet.
If history serves me, Fort George did
fall to the Americans.
Why aren't you wearing the comb now,
Janet?
Oh, perhaps I shall.
If, uh...
marauding Yankees ever attack Avonlea.
Good afternoon, ladies.
I couldn't help overhearing your
laughter, and that brought to mind
chapter 7, verse 5.
It is better to hear the rebuke of the
wise than for a man to hear the song of
fools.
Behas me.
A little too much inspiration leaks into
his vocal cords from time to time.
Perhaps we should have told him to go
fly a kite.
And now you can see the importance
of the rule of the 100 strokes.
Toothbrush and hairbrush.
Well, ladies, let's see if we don't eat
soon I shall drop dead.
You can bring in the refreshments now.
I really wish you would all try to
concentrate.
Now, next on our agenda, posture and
profile.
How about the posture and profile of
Edward Ray?
That is hardly the level of discourse
for the Avonley Young Ladies Colloquium
for social... With Thomas Nisbet there?
Do you like Thomas Nisbet? Do you know
what you sound like? Geeks.
A bunch of silly geeks.
Help eat in the kitchen.
Now, posture and profile are vital to a
good first impression.
You know, it's not fair.
Can you imagine if we decided to swim
uncovered?
I said stop it.
I've been waiting an hour and a half in
that stuffy old kitchen where you talked
and talked and talked, boring everyone
to death. No one was bored.
Was anyone bored?
You'll be imprisoned in your room
forever.
Look again!
The others went home. They had enough
social betterments for one day.
Can't you just tell Aunt Janet you're
sorry?
Sarah, it's an heirloom.
The gift of that comb means the world to
Mother.
I'll bet it was worth a lot of money.
Don't worry, Felicity. It'll show up.
Bet you it won't.
Bet you Felicity will be in trouble for
years over this one.
Felix! I just want to be there when
Mother and Father find out.
Mother and Father aren't going to find
out, Felix.
It could be months before Mother even
wears the comb.
You can't keep it a secret.
Don't you remember what Reverend
Fitzsimmons said about sins and
Promise me, Felix, you'll not say a word
to Mother or Father about the comb.
Promise me or I'll run you through. I
promise.
Fit in your hand.
Now rub it on your heart.
Didn't either of you listen to a word
the reverend said?
Janet, don't forget to wear your new
comb.
I know,
I know, we're late.
You don't happen to know where my new
comb is, do you?
I haven't the slightest inkling of where
it could be right now.
I swear I left it in here with the baby
and all.
Let's get going. I'll find another time
then.
You said you'd wear it this week.
I decided it wasn't really a church sort
of comb.
Grandmama wore it at my christening.
Angel's voice will deafen us, crying, Ye
dead!
The judge is come!
Arise! And meet your instant doom!
I think you'd be proud to wear such a
fine king family heirloom. How else
could recognize quality?
The king's in qualities measured by
glitter alone.
Will come!
Will ye be cast into the lake of...
He didn't.
that comb to every family wedding and
funeral.
How do you think that made us feel,
Janet?
so kind as to play hymn number 247.
I was wondering if we have a little word
about the pulpit. Yes, Webster and I.
Felicity, are you well?
Felicity knows that her soul is like a
black -dented old pot.
Who could possibly be well after that
sermon?
I wasn't listening to the sermon. I was
listening to your... Parents argue about
the comb.
Well, everyone was arguing.
I heard Mrs. Lawson say that Mother was
ungrateful.
But Reverend Fitzsimmons knows.
He was looking directly at me throughout
the whole sermon.
You're all upset and bleak, so why don't
you just take your medicine?
Because if I could just find the comb,
everything would be fine.
Those wards never had a sense of
history. That's the problem.
I was a girl.
I admired great -grandma more than
anyone else in the family. It has
do with it. If I'd known that Janet was
going to feel that way about the coma,
I'd have kept it myself.
Oh, that's enough, Olivia.
Janet promised to fulfill her familial
obligation, so... Only after we bullied
her into it.
You'd think she'd be proud to wear such
a gift. I'm sure Aunt Janet never
intended to cause such an uproar.
I'm sure she'd be happy to wear it to a
special occasion, like... like a ball.
Oh, Sarah, don't make excuses for her.
But wasn't the whole point that you gave
it to her as a gift?
I mean, now you're all badgering her
about it. It just doesn't seem fair.
Maybe she had good reason for it.
Like what?
Now you're badgering Sarah, really,
Olivia.
It'll do no good to stew about it.
Oh, Janet will wear the comb in her own
good time, I hope.
While we're all still alive and
breathing, I hope.
Sarah, what are you doing?
I'm trying to answer a question.
Oh, what question?
About the world.
About when it began and when it'll end.
End?
Oh, wherever did you get such an
outlandish notion?
Eddie, can't she even ask a simple
question?
I mean, obviously, if the world began at
some point in time, then it's logically
going to end.
You've been talking with Jasper too
long, Olivia.
Well?
Felix has been scaring Felicity half to
death because the Reverend mentioned it
in his sermon.
I'm just trying to prove that it won't
happen.
Never your mind, child.
If the world does end, it certainly
won't be in my lifetime.
Or yours.
I dropped them jacks.
They spilled everywhere.
Go get me some eggs.
Pardon? Get me some egg.
But I collected this morning. Don't
argue with me, young lady. I'm feeling
dangerous.
Thank you, Mr. King.
Well, I'm sorry to startle you like
that. I was engrossed in next week's
Jacob and the Angel.
I'm afraid your kite is probably on the
way to Africa by now.
I have quite a few of them, actually.
Do you normally fly them in the dead of
winter?
Neither rain nor snow nor sleet nor hail
can stop the truly devoted, Mr. King.
I find the making and flying of kites
very fulfilling.
Sort of a...
Fishing line to heaven, is it?
Yes, exactly, Mr. King.
Well, I'm sorry I surprised you like
that.
Mr. King, I'm afraid you distracted the
congregation somewhat on Sunday.
No, no.
When a congregation does not listen, it
is the capability of the preacher which
falls in doubt.
We were taught the voice is a preacher's
most valuable tool.
It's another reason I started flying
kites. I would send them up as far as I
could and preach to them.
You know, learn to control my voice,
make it strong.
Tell me, sir, did you find when you
preached very loudly that the kites flew
higher? No.
Don't believe in all this end -of -the
-world nonsense.
According to the ancient seers, the end
of the world would be foretold by seven
unmistakable signs.
Who cares what that trashy magazine
says?
Fine, then. I guess you don't want to
hear the signs.
Tell us some, Felix.
The very earth shall tremble with great
force, killing the multitudes and
reducing to embers. A great city by the
sea.
San Francisco.
The earthquake.
Those predictions are so vague.
Do you want to hear the signs about the
approaching ice age?
No, Felix, put your stupid magazine
away.
Sarah, what did you find out about
Doomsday?
Well, apparently it will go something
like the weighing of sugar at the
General Store, substituting the sugar
for the good deeds and the sins for the
lead weights.
Well, then, in that case, I should do
quite well.
Currently, the loss of the comb is the
only black mark on the ledger of my
easily outweighed by all my good deeds.
Don't forget that you're ruining her
parents' marriage.
Not to mention the fact that Aunt Olivia
and Aunt Hedy will react when they find
out that great -great -grandma's comb is
gone.
Oh, I must find that comb.
Felix, where exactly were we when I
started to squeeze your head?
No, it's great.
None of these will do.
Hardly. I think you're just going to
have to tell them the truth. It gave me
quite a start, whatever it was. I could
imagine.
An angel? Well, the trumpet passed right
over the psalmist.
Must be that Reverend Fitzsimmons.
Not your run -of -the -mill preacher.
Did you hear that?
I wouldn't have believed it if I hadn't
seen it for myself.
Elvira, chamomile soap and a packet of
washing tablets?
Why don't you tell that one to the
paper?
What happened?
At the car stairs funeral, in the middle
of the eulogy, Henry sat straight up in
his casket, looked all around at the
candles and said, whose birthday is it
anyway?
Don't say.
Did you hear that?
Felicity, I'm sure there's a perfectly
logical explanation.
And just the other day, old man Steele's
cow gave birth to a two -headed calf.
I heard about that.
It's the ninth.
Felix. Where's the magazine?
See, it's true.
Better find that comb fast, Felicity, or
you'll be roasting in the eternal
flames.
Felicity, are you all right?
You look like it's the end of the world.
Felicity, don't go out there.
You can't go out there.
Why not?
It's them.
Who?
The four horsemen of the apocalypse.
What we needed to bring her to her
senses.
Or find that comb.
That's no fun at all.
Felix.
Oh, all right.
How? Who found you when you were lost in
the woods?
And who figured out why the kingdom's
well went dry?
Peg Bowen.
What has the finding of this comb got to
do with the end of the world?
Felicity stole Gregory Grandmother
King's comb, then lost it, and she never
anyone about it. And now she's worried
that the end of the world will come and
she'll roast down the devil's pitchfork.
Shut up, Felix.
I don't suppose the girlie has
considered just telling her mother the
facing the consequences of her
foolishness?
That's what I suggested.
I wanted to, but there was never the
right moment.
Couldn't you just help us find the comb?
You found Jane Spry's lost cat last
month. The comb doesn't meow outside my
in the middle of the night.
And the whole point of the end of the
world is that it takes you by surprise.
But there have been so many signs.
Earthquake, fires, a typhoon in India.
Those are signs, all right.
The truth is, every so often, the
measure of the world is taken.
So far...
There's always been more virtue than
evil, more good people than bad.
But if that balance ever changes, stay
evil.
The thing to do is admit your weaknesses
and failings before the world
ends. I'm going to be wanting your
solemn vow.
that whatever you discover here in this
room today goes no further.
I don't have to rub spit on my heart, do
I?
Disgusting, that.
No, a simple promise will do, lad.
Do I have your word?
Tomorrow night, the voracious wolf will
run across the sky.
And if the balance of evil in the world
is more than the balance of good, the
moon will be swallowed by the ravening
wolf.
Sure, but it doesn't say anything in my
magazine.
Whoa!
Lunar eclipse.
What are we going to do?
Do you think the world really will end
tomorrow night?
We should go to the church.
You can't say a thing for the church.
I mean to pray.
We should all go on top of the barn.
The lighthouse.
Instruct our hurricanes and lightning.
We'll get a good view from there.
And got through the wave before we
marked it. Drat.
I just wish I could find that comb.
I wish we could warn the others. No.
We made a solemn vow.
We're all agreed then.
We'll meet at the lighthouse tomorrow
night.
Did you lose something?
Alec, are you trying to give me
apoplexy?
I better start wearing a bell. I seem to
be the most frightening man in the
county.
Do you remember that dreadful pipe your
father gave me as a wedding present?
Of course I do. You fouled the air with
it for six months.
Exactly. And you know why? Because I
wanted to keep peace in the family. I
didn't want to insult your family, and
so I went out of my way to please your
father, which was not easy.
Yes, Alec. The comb was given to you as
a sincere gesture, and Hedy and Olivia
will be hurt if you don't wear it. I am
aware of my obligation to your family,
Alec, and I will fulfill it. When?
Well, I don't know.
find the right moment. Oh, Alec, don't
try to blackmail me.
They don't know it's their last night on
earth.
Well, what else would you call it? Well,
there is... Stop!
It is only a thing.
Surely what is best in our family has
nothing to do with things.
Look, I certainly love you both. And the
baby and Cecily and... and even Felix.
despite all the material things that
I've been denied.
Well, all right, I'll wear it. The new
pulpit arrives tomorrow. I'll wear it to
the ceremony.
Thank you.
I'll see to it our loving children get
back to bed.
Good night, Mother.
Sorry the Yankees didn't burn Fort
George to the ground.
Why a trip to Carmody? What's there that
I can't pick up for you and have on a
leash? Oh, well, I don't want to burden
you with details. It's women's business.
Oh, I see.
You'll be back in time for the new
pulpit?
The time to spare.
I think I might finish cleaning the
carpets and some of those other
chores that you've been struggling with
this week. What has come over you? This
whole house has been turned upside down.
She's combing it from top to bottom.
She found a watch, Bob, I lost, oh,
eight years ago.
Oh? Come across anything else of
interest?
No.
Well, then obviously it's nowhere in
this house.
What is it?
Well, anything Felicity hasn't found, of
course.
She's cleaning the place like the
devil's after her.
Well, can you do it?
Certainly. Oh, it has to look so much
like the original that no one can tell
difference. Oh.
This afternoon.
Thank you.
Beautiful. Wonderful.
That's dirty maritime oak.
Hallelujah.
Hallelujah. Hallelujah.
It's going to be late.
Yes, Alec, I'm coming.
Maybe I should take the Bible with you
tonight.
The Bible? Why?
Oh, just in case.
In case of what?
The end of the world.
Sometimes I worry about those children.
I'm a king.
I told you I'd wear it and wear it. I
will.
All right.
What do you think you're doing?
Is it the end of the world?
No use in being hungry.
What's that in your hand, Rachel Cotton?
Yes, it is.
Whatever for?
Well, I seem to have a bit of earache.
That's what.
Not that it's any of your business,
Petty King.
If he yells at us again tonight, we're
going to wish we had some of that
Olivia, she'd better be wearing that
comb.
Alec. Just give her some time.
Slight against our family, that's what
it is.
Alec, should I go check on Janet? She's
taking ages.
Look, now she's afraid to face us, is
she?
Now, Eddie.
How does it look?
Oh, Janet, it's awful.
May I remind you, that is great
-grandmama's comb of courage.
I had no idea that it... Oh, I do recall
it looking somewhat more elegant on
her. No, it doesn't fit as I remember on
you, Janet.
Well, what should I do with it then?
Perhaps you should take it off, Janet.
There's one good thing.
Someday you'll be able to pass it on to
Felicity.
You can tell it isn't a normal evening,
can't you?
Yes.
It's so very bright and mysterious.
It's a good thing Mr. Potts led the
lighthouse.
I wish Gus were home.
Shall we go up to the top?
No.
Let's wait until it's really happy.
Good.
This thing is getting heavy.
What did you bring, Sarah?
Some photographs of my parents before
they get married.
That's not very practical.
Oh, it certainly is.
What did you bring, Felicity?
My report cards.
I thought they might stand me in good
stead as a sort of record of my
achievements. What about you, Cecily?
I brought Dagar. I wouldn't go anywhere
without him.
Just like Felix wouldn't go anywhere
without food. You'll be glad when it
happens that someone thought to pack a
lunch.
Full form.
It's just a cloud.
I was out in the fields the other day.
The beautiful white fields of Avonlea.
Practicing my sermon.
and was surprised by a man out walking.
So surprised, in fact, that I fell
backwards and struck my head.
And it occurred to me then that if I had
not been hollering at the heavens like
a fool, I wouldn't have been so
surprised.
And that led me to think that perhaps
sometimes silence is a better tool for a
preacher than bluster, a sin of pride.
to place the loudness of my voice above
the importance of the message in the
words. So, rather than my voice alone,
let us raise our
voices together in song and bless this
pulpit.
This fellow may work out after all.
Peg Bowen said we should try to clear
our guilty conscience.
That's right.
My conscience is clear.
What's a conscience?
It's a record of our weaknesses and
failings. I have something, Felicity.
I used the Loving Cup that you won for
naming the books of the Bible as a
tadpole trap.
Well, boys will be boys.
I won. I also used a pair of your
bloomers for a flag on the top of our
treehouse. Who saw them?
Well, let's see.
Everyone.
I forgive you, Felix.
I read your diary.
I think we've had enough confessions.
I read it out loud.
To who?
All my friends.
We were camping out.
Everyone laughed about the gushy parts
of Gus Pike.
Gus Pike?
Gus Pike didn't laugh. His ears burned a
fierce red.
You read it to Gus Pike?
Felicity, don't lose your temper. The
end is nigh.
Hang, you say.
Felicity, it will look very bad for you
if you hurt her. Feel it.
I don't care. He deserves it.
The wolf. The wolf is here.
Felicity, don't you want to unburden
yourself before the end?
No, I'd rather not.
I do.
Sarah wants in arithmetic.
That's the spirit.
I have something to confess.
I feigned illness on occasion to avoid
Sunday services.
Doesn't anyone want to hear what I've
done?
I'm black -hearted and vain.
I stole Mother's comb and then lost it
and didn't have the courage to tell
anyone about it.
Oh, I wish I'd told Mother.
If the world were ending now, I swear I
would tell her.
Digger took the comb.
What?
That's what I wanted to tell you.
Why didn't you take it away from him?
He liked it. Besides, I thought you'd
brain him like you did Felix.
But, Cecily, Digger is a dog.
I was just going to let him play with it
a while, but I think he buried it. Oh,
this is a terrible thing that you've
done, Cecily.
I'd hate to see what will happen during
your judgment.
Look!
We've turned the balance of evil.
You still have me to deal with, however.
Oh, my stomach.
Well, you are up early.
Mother, I have something to tell you.
I borrowed your comb and then lost it.
I'm so sorry. I know how much it meant
to you and Father.
Oh, Felicity, you should have known
better than that.
After I expressly told you not to.
I have something much worse to confess,
Felicity. I have no right to be angry
with you.
I beg your pardon?
I thought I'd lost it.
So I went to Carmody and spent all our
mad money on a duplicate.
Turns out all I had to do was simply put
the thing on and Hedy would have
understood immediately why I hated it so
much.
I shall surely go to hell.
I've heard the confessions are good for
the soul.
Perhaps if we told Father... Oh, I think
it's good enough that we told each
other, Felicity.
Now, if the real comb doesn't show up,
we're safe.
What's this?
The scavenger's thrown all our food
overnight?
Felix, can you get down here this
minute? I have some questions for you.
Get out of there.
Go on. Go on.
What's this?
Well, I'll... Janet!